A biblical theology of generosity does not start with tithing, or even Jesus' command
to be generous to the poor.
It starts before time and space, with who God is.
Since the beginning of Scripture, the world itself was created as an act of generous love,
with God as a joyful, generous host, the world as His home,
and you and I as His special guests.
And from the inner nature of God, giving becomes our nature.
And little by little, He makes our souls incandescent.
Well, I'm excited this morning to start a third practice in a series that we started back in the beginning of this year called Practicing the Way.
Yeah, some of you are more excited than others.
I love to hear that as well.
And Corey last week preached a standalone message, but really it wasn't a standalone message.
It was the lead-in to this message.
He preached the message on Christoformity or the goal of every disciple of Jesus to be conformed to the image of Jesus.
That Christianity is not just about hearing the teachings of Jesus and agreeing with them, saying yes and amen to them.
That hearing the teachings of Jesus, that submitting your life to the Lordship of Jesus is actually about doing what He says.
Becoming like who He was.
He was at the end of His famous sermon on the mountain.
He said, "Blessed are those who hear these words of mine and put them into practice."
So the goal of this series, it's a church-wide curriculum that we're going to be running over the next three years or so.
And it's aimed at helping us intentionally build habits and practices into our lives that will help us obey the teachings and practices of Jesus.
That will help us become conformed to the image of Jesus.
Language matters, right?
We often, the American church often identifies themselves by the word Christian.
And there's nothing wrong with the word Christian.
But the word Christian has come to mean I intellectually agree with the Bible and Jesus.
Jesus uses different language like disciple, apprentice, follower.
That we've been invited into so much more than just agreeing with what He says, but actually living into His kingdom on earth as it is in heaven.
So, do me a favor, if you were here February, March, when we did the fasting and prayer practices, can you raise your hand?
Okay, keep it up, a good chunk of you.
All right, now, if during that series you changed, added, adapted some version of, new version of prayer or fasting to your life, can you leave your hand up?
Okay, now, keep your hand up if you are still consistently practicing something new that you added to your life from that series.
Okay, not bad.
We got some people here, that's good.
Hey, I did not do that practice to make you feel guilt or shame or condemnation.
I love the language of this curriculum, and it's actually the language of Jesus.
They say, we make invitations, you make decisions.
This is not like a guilt trip, legalistic, you have to do all of these things in order to be a good Christian.
This is taking a deep look at the teachings of Jesus and inviting us to adopt practices, the goal of which are to be conformed to the image of Jesus.
If you try a new practice, if you implement a habit in your life, and you find that it doesn't help you become more like Jesus, don't do it.
The goal of these practices, the goal of these invitations is that we would respond to, receive, get internalized the word of Jesus, and allow it to transform us from the inside out.
If we are just doing tasks so that we look religiously holy, we've missed the point altogether, and we're wasting our time.
And so, no shame, no guilt, these are invitations into practices that align with the vision of Jesus for the kingdom of God on earth as it is in heaven.
Make sense?
So, our final practice, as you have probably noticed by now, for 2024 will be on generosity, particularly generosity of our stuff.
Is anybody going to get up and leave?
I thought about it.
No.
Not because stuff is the only thing that we can be generous with, but because we have to focus on one thing.
And if we get generous with our stuff, I think we will naturally become more generous with our time, with our relationships, with our influence, et cetera.
Make sense?
A couple disclaimers.
One, I usually hate talking about money, wealth, finances in church.
Anybody else hate listening to pastors talk about money, wealth, finances in church?
A couple reasons.
One, generosity is not a strong suit of mine.
I'm just going to be totally vulnerable and upfront with you.
I struggle to implement these practices.
I struggle to embrace the kingdom vision of Christ's open-handed generosity with all things.
Not only do I struggle with it, but I feel like the church throughout the past 50 years or so that I've been able to observe recordings of have seen pastors do a bad job of talking about money in the past.
It can be really self-serving, and when the budget gets low, you can say, all right, we'll preach a sermon and tell people to give the church the money.
That is not the goal of this series.
The goal of this series is to invite you to embrace Jesus' mindset of generosity and to consider putting it into practice.
So I'm actually really excited about this series because the more I interact with Christ's teaching on money and wealth, the more I am convinced that obedience to these teachings will ultimately lead to your peace and your abundance and your joy.
Amen.
Even though it's countercultural to what the world tells us will lead to peace, abundance, and joy.
We'll get to that in a minute.
And maybe you're here and you're like, okay, cool.
I like it.
That's great.
But four weeks?
You're going to talk to us about our money for four weeks?
That seems like a lot.
Well, many scholars estimate that around 25% of Christ's teaching directly deal with money or wealth, which means if I am going to apply Corey's message from last week about being conformed to the image of Jesus, I owe you guys at least nine more sermons on money before the year's over.
Man, I thought you guys were going to laugh harder at that one.
I was really excited about that one.
All right.
Last disclaimer, the room, our room, this room, which I am proud of and thankful for, is actually extremely economically diverse.
We have people from all different spectrums and all different levels of wealth.
And so my intent is not to give you specifics on how to apply these principles to your financial situation.
My goal is to give broad principles that Jesus teaches about money and invite you, personally, if you're an apprentice of Jesus, a follower of Jesus, to take that to God in prayer and say, God, how does this principle apply to me, to my financial situation?
What does it look like for me to live these things out?
And I trust that the Holy Spirit will do that work for you far better than I could do it if I stood up here and put it in my outline.
Sound good?
Cool.
Let's pray and get started.
Father, everything we have is not ours.
Everything on this planet is yours and it is your gift to us.
God, may we learn to embrace that mindset 24/7, 365 days a year.
That everything that we think is ours is actually a gift from you and trust it to us.
And may we learn to use it in light of your kingdom vision.
Not so that people will think we're holy.
Not so that people will look at us and say, wow, how generous are they.
But so that the kingdom of God will be more visible on earth as it is in heaven.
Holy Spirit, do whatever it is that you want to do in this room today for your glory, for our good.
In Jesus' name I pray.
Amen.
Okay.
As Americans, our nation was built on the idea of life, liberty, and the pursuit of...
Property and money.
Happiness, property.
And yet, many recent studies show that Americans are much less happy on average than many other countries in the world.
The study that I looked at said Americans are the 23rd happiest citizens on planet earth.
Not only that, but we function in a capitalistic society that boasts about something called the American dream.
Where many believe if you work hard enough and you make the right decisions, any one of us can attain a better life.
A better life.
And that better life is often tied to economic status and upward mobility.
Our nation has discipled into us this idea that if you want to be happy, you have to have more stuff.
If you want to be happy, you have to have a larger bank account.
With that as a backdrop, why might citizens of one of the wealthiest nations in the world,
who are just a little bit of hard work and a few right decisions away from climbing the economic ladder, be so unhappy?
Why might we struggle with happiness even in a nation full of freedom and abundance?
Well, my question is, is it possible that we have bought the wrong idea about where true happiness comes from?
Is it possible that we've been persuaded to play the wrong game altogether?
Is it possible that we have just naturally, without really realizing and embraced the cultural values rather than the values of the kingdom of God?
Well, to answer those questions, we're going to look at Jesus' teaching in Matthew 6.
So if you have your Bibles, you want to turn there or open there up on your tablets or your phones, we're going to get there.
And as you open to Matthew 6, give you some context.
His teaching in Matthew 6 on money, wealth, and possessions is in the middle of his famous Sermon on the Mount.
This is the premier summary and collection of Christ's teachings about the kingdom of God.
It's all about how followers of Jesus can live in a way that aligns our lives with the values of the kingdom of God on earth as it is in heaven.
What is the Sermon on the Mount as Jesus saying, if you want to live into the future kingdom that will come and reign and rule for eternity,
these are the things that you can begin to do now on earth that represent what will be true in heaven forever and ever.
Scholar Stanley Hauerwas summarizes it this way about the Sermon on the Mount.
He said, "It is the reality of the age to come made possible in its time."
There is a time coming when Jesus will rule and reign on earth for eternity.
And the Sermon on the Mount, the principles laid out in the Sermon on the Mount,
are how we can begin to embody those principles here on earth, even if they're countercultural.
Except they're always going to be countercultural, so yes.
So it might not come as a surprise to you, when Jesus addresses money in light of the kingdom of God,
it flies in the face of typical earthly wisdom, which reminds me of the proverb.
There is a way that seems right to a person, but in the end leads to death.
I think this is a helpful summary of how many of us in the American culture have embraced the cultural ideas of money, wealth, status, power, finances.
Seems right. Makes sense. Do the math. Put it in the spreadsheet. It works.
Except it doesn't.
This is one reason I think many, both inside and outside the church, in our culture, struggle with happiness.
I think it's possible that we've adopted a distorted view of money and possessions that lead us to be controlled by either fear or greed.
And depending on where you're at in the economic status,
probably depends on whether or not you're struggling more with fear or with greed.
We'll get to that in a little bit.
All the while, Jesus is inviting us to embrace his view of money and possessions
that ultimately will lead us to the peace and abundance that we're longing for.
He calls it the abundant life.
Okay.
With all that in context,
he actually has three really short, quick summary statements about money and possessions here.
We're going to read one at a time and try and glean some principles from them.
First, Matthew six, verse 19.
Jesus says these words, red letter.
Do not lay up for yourself treasures on earth where moth and rust destroy,
where thieves break in and steal.
But lay up for yourselves treasures in heaven where neither moth nor rust destroy
and where thieves do not break in and steal.
For where your treasure is, there your heart will be also."
Sound like the Son of God on earth in the flesh?
Amen.
Jesus very clearly and concisely addresses one of the core human impulses,
the desire to store up material things for ourselves and for our loved ones in the most reliable sources.
This is a core human desire.
It always has been and it always will be.
We seek to find security, stability, safety for us and for those that we love.
Humans have always had this desire.
But what's interesting to me is that you will see that Jesus does not rebuke this desire altogether.
He doesn't say don't store up for yourselves things.
He just changes what it is that we're storing up and where it is that we're storing it up.
He redefines what is valuable and where it should be stored up.
His main argument, his main argument is that anything we store up on earth is subject to the harsh realities of this fallen world.
Does anybody feel that this morning?
Amen.
That the things that we store up are subject to the harsh realities of this world.
I'm sure most of us, probably all of us have had this experience of investing in or accumulating stuff that we thought would give us either security, safety.
I have enough.
My family has enough.
We're okay.
All of our basic needs are met.
Security or pleasure.
I'm gonna invest money in things that bring me joy.
I'm sure all of us have had an experience where we invest things in either security or in pleasure and it fell woefully short.
It left us wanting.
I know for me and Marissa, I don't know, she might be taking care of the baby.
It feels like every time we meet a savings goal, right?
Like we set a goal and we're like, man, this is really how much we need to have if everything breaks and all the stuff.
I meet the savings goal and then everything breaks.
Am I the only one?
It's like, oh, we finally got there.
And then the car starts smoking and the refrigerator starts blinking.
Like two nights ago, the dishwasher was just like, water was spilling out and like lights were blinking and I was like, ah, isn't it perfect that I'm preaching on generosity and trusting God with our stuff and stuff is breaking.
Moth, rust, they destroy our safety and security.
We make what we think is good stock investments and then red line instead of green line, right?
This happens on earth.
We store up things that we think are in reliable places and they're not nearly as reliable as we think.
And so we think we're going to find the security that we want.
But in the back of our mind, because we've had these experiences, even when we get to that place of security in the back of our mind, we're like, is it enough?
Will it be safe?
Will it be destroyed?
Will something get in the way of this?
So the security, we think we're going to have it and ultimately leads to fear.
And then pleasure, we invest in things that we think will give us pleasure.
And the vacation ends too quickly.
The home improvements become outdated.
The newest toy or trinket ends up in next year's garage sale.
And so when we buy things or invest in things that we think will give us pleasure and then don't give us the pleasure that they promised or that we thought they would give us, what does that lead to?
Leads to greed.
All right, well, this thing didn't work, so I'll get a better toy, a bigger toy, a newer toy.
I'll go on a longer trip.
I'll invest more money in this thing or that thing.
And it leads us to constantly chasing after this desire that stuff will satisfy the longing of our heart.
And Jesus says, don't store up for yourself treasures on earth because it's not going to lead to the satisfaction that you think it is.
Jesus is pointing out something we all know deep down but rarely allowed to influence our decisions.
Earthly wealth is fleeting.
Every effort to store up stuff on earth will not accomplish what we want it to accomplish in our hearts and our lives.
So Jesus' solution is sell everything, live in the plains.
No.
It's not that crazy.
He just says, store up your stuff, store up different kind of stuff in a more reliable location.
Firstly, he says, store up your stuff in heaven.
Now, this is broadly misinterpreted, right?
We think of heaven mostly influenced more by culture than by the Scriptures.
We think of heaven as this, like, spiritual realm in the sky that we're going to go to when we die.
And storing up treasures in heaven means that if we do good things on earth, then we'll have a bigger mansion in heaven.
That's not actually what Jesus is saying here.
Heaven, in the Hebrew mind, was actually the place where God's presence dwelled with God's people.
So heaven for Jesus is the kingdom of God.
Investing in the kingdom of God on earth as it is in heaven.
It's doing kingdom things here and now because heaven will come to earth.
And what we do with the kingdom in mind on earth will last as the kingdom comes to earth.
So he says, invest in heavenly things.
And the treasures he's talking about here is that how we invest our possessions in a way that demonstrates our love for God and neighbor.
If we use our stuff, our time, our energy, our resources, our wealth, if we invest these things in loving God with our whole heart, soul, mind, and strength, and loving our neighbor as ourselves, we will be storing up for ourselves treasures in heaven.
We store up treasures for heaven when we use our stuff to do heavenly things on earth.
My cliff notes summary of what Jesus is saying here is he says, I know, I know that you think.
And this is, when I made my notes, I really thought this was bold that I was going to try and make a cliff notes version of what Jesus had to say.
Right?
Like this, it feels weird.
So take it for what it is.
Ryan Miller's cliff notes version of Jesus.
Okay.
I know you think accumulating stuff on earth will lead to security and pleasure.
But in the end, it will lead to fear and greed.
However, if you invest your stuff in my kingdom, it will give you the ultimate security and pleasure that you are seeking.
He goes on in verse 21, just for good measure, to make sure that we don't over-spiritualize this teaching or apply it to other people.
Don't we tend to do that?
Like, yeah, that's actually right.
And that person needs to hear it because they have more money than I do.
Right?
So he makes just a really clear statement.
Where your treasure is, there your heart will be also.
So he says, if you're not sure if you're doing these things, if you're not sure if you're investing in, if you're storing up for yourself treasures in heaven, just look at how you spend your money.
Look at what you treasure.
Look at the investment you put into things and stuff and money.
Is it for my kingdom and my purposes?
Or your kingdom and your purposes?
That will reveal to you where your heart is.
And again, remember, this isn't about guilt, condemnation, or shame.
And if you're feeling like, oh man, I've never really interacted with these teachings.
I think I spend a lot of my time, money, and possessions on me.
And I don't really think about the kingdom of God.
Jesus isn't here trying to make you feel like a terrible person.
He's actually inviting you into the thing that's going to give you the life and experience that you're longing for.
Amen.
This is the creator of the universe saying, this is what you were intended to live for.
You're trying to get it in all the wrong places.
Searching for love?
All the wrong places?
This is Jesus' first teaching on money and wealth.
Anybody uncomfortable yet?
Okay, you guys are doing better than I am.
All right.
Verse 22.
The eye is the lamp of the body.
So if your eye is healthy, your whole body will be full of light.
But if your eye is bad, your whole body will be full of darkness.
If then the light in you is darkness, how great is the darkness.
Now you guys know exactly what Jesus is saying here, so I don't need any further explanation, right?
This passage, it seems a bit cryptic.
It seems a bit confusing.
It seems like, Jesus, are you trying to hide some kind of deep spiritual truth in here that we don't know?
No, you're just not Hebrew.
So it doesn't make as much sense to you.
But the passage would make a lot more sense to the original audience.
It's a word play rich with Hebraic symbolism that I don't have the time, nor am I particularly qualified to explain to you.
I will be sharing a podcast in the newsletter this week that does an incredible job at deep diving just these two verses.
So if you want to go deeper, if you want to go further, I will send that to you, and I hope that you find help in it.
But, I can't just skip it, so I'm going to do my best.
Here's my best at simplifying what Jesus was saying.
Hebrew culture, they viewed the eye as the window into the soul.
It's not totally foreign from us, right?
Like, when we have deep relationships with people, we look them in the eye, and we feel like there's this connection, this understanding.
Like, I can understand who this person is better when I look them in the eye.
In the eye, it's weird.
Isn't it weird when you're talking to somebody and they won't look in the eye?
It's like something shady, sketchy, something's going on here.
So, the Hebrews, they had this idea that when you look somebody in the eye, it was a window through their, a window into their soul.
And therefore, what they directed their attention to, where their eyes were gazing, where they were looking, where they were pursuing things, was ultimately revealing what was true about them on the inside.
Does that make sense?
Jesus makes a different version of this statement where he says, "Out of the overflow of the heart, the mouth speaks."
Right?
It's not what goes into the mouth that defiles the person, it's what comes out.
This is the same idea, that where we direct, that you can tell a lot about a person's soul by how they direct their eyes.
And it actually had become like a really, a word play here in Hebrew.
Actually, in the Old Testament, the term good eye was regularly used to describe a generous person.
If you had a good eye, people said, "Okay, there's something, you have peace internally with God and others, and that impacts the way that you handle your stuff."
And bad eye was used to describe a stingy or selfish person.
It's like when you see somebody being stingy or selfish or hoarding things for themselves, it reveals to you something about their internal relationship with God and others.
And this is not a foreign idea.
It's spoken in a foreign way, but I think we can all resonate with this, right?
When you see somebody that's generous, that's kind, that's giving, you're like, "Oh, that person has something inside that's different."
It reveals their relationship with God and neighbor.
And Jesus is ultimately saying here that how you view and relate to God will determine whether you have a good eye or a bad eye, whether you live generously or selfishly, right?
It's not just, we can't just change our behavior when it comes to generosity.
You can't just say, "Oh, I heard a sermon on generosity, so I'm going to give more."
It starts at the heart.
It starts at how we view God and how we view others.
John Mark Comer, who is one of the builders of this curriculum, summarizes this way.
He says that, "Those with a good eye have an abundance mindset, and those with a bad eye have a scarcity mindset."
So the abundant mindset says, "There is a good and loving creator.
I am his beloved child.
Everything that I have is a gift from him to be used and shared for his glory and the good of others."
Right?
There is a good heavenly father who created all of the earth and has given us all that we need for life and flourishing.
He is good.
He has a good purpose in mind.
And if he is God, and if he is good, then there is more than enough resources.
I don't need to be fearful or greedy.
I don't need to fight and war and compete for stuff.
I can live with an open hand.
I can share what I have with those who are in need.
Jesus will later go on to say in the Sermon on the Mount, "Look at the birds of the air.
Look at the lilies of the field."
They do not worry about what they are going to eat or what they are going to wear.
Because they understand they are part of a bigger creation from a loving father who will provide.
If this is how we view God, it will change everything about how we view our resources.
It will lead us to a life full of peace and generosity.
Or as Jesus puts it, we will have a good eye.
The scarcity mindset says there is no benevolent God.
He either doesn't exist or he isn't good, or at least he doesn't care about you and your family.
This is a dog-eat-dog world, so I have to look out for myself.
Other people are a competition for possible resources.
And they ultimately get in the way of my security and my happiness.
If this is how we view God, or a lack thereof, it will lead us to be consumed by fear and greed.
Or as Jesus puts it, we'll have a bad eye.
Right?
We'll be consumed by just trying to carve out a path for ourselves where we feel secure and we feel happy.
And it's like grasping at the wind.
So, the reality is, I would guess, pastorally, as I've interacted with many of you in this room,
the reality is that we probably all fall somewhere in between these two extremes.
Right?
Like, I painted the picture of as far on the opposite end of the spectrum as possible.
I doubt that many of us would raise our hand and say,
every moment of every day, I live with an abundance mindset.
I know that God's going to provide for me.
Everything I have is his.
I freely give.
I freely receive.
Right?
Like, that's, you know, Jesus.
So, you know, somewhere on this scale, most of us are somewhere in the middle.
Some of us might trend towards a scarcity mindset.
But my goal here is for us to just think about where, how is it that I view God in light of the stuff that I have
and the stuff that I feel that I need.
And as your pastor, I really would love to stand up here and tell you that I embody the abundance mindset.
I just, everything comes from God and I need nothing and I will go in peace.
Right.
So, here's the thing.
I agree with these principles.
Right?
I listen to Jesus' teaching and I say, that is right and good, yes and amen.
But then I wake up and I walk around my house and make note of the things that are broken
and the things that need to be fixed.
And I look at my wife and I look at my baby and I say, there's not going to be enough.
There's never going to be enough.
I've got to get a second Job.
I've got to work harder.
I've got to go do more stuff.
And then I look at my friends who have more stuff than me and I'm like, man, why do they have more stuff than me?
I'm slaving it out for the Lord and they have more stuff than me.
Right?
It's dark.
It's dirty and I feel myself being pulled towards it on a regular basis.
And Jesus is saying, you think that having, like Ryan, you think that just a few more dollars in your savings account,
one more appliance that's not broke, like you think that's actually going to make you happy and secure and satisfied.
The next appliance will break next week.
Like there's never going to be a season.
I think many of us, we long for the season where we sit down on our couch and look around at everything.
And nothing is broken and everything works.
The engine light is not going to come on next week.
And Jesus is saying, Jesus is saying that isn't reality.
We live in a fallen world.
Stuff breaks.
Things get destroyed.
Moth and rust, they eat.
There's never going to be a season in your life where you feel like you have everything that you want.
I mean, there's studies about wealthy people.
I heard a story one time about a financial broker who was talking to a person with a million dollars.
It was like, how much will be enough?
And they were like, 10 million.
He was talking to somebody with 10 million.
How much will be enough?
100 million.
Right?
Like even people who have more than others, they still think there's more.
We got to get more.
There has to be more.
More security.
More pleasure.
More.
This is the scarcity mindset.
And Jesus says, if you want to be healthy, if you want to have abundant life, you've got to learn to trust me more than you trust yourself.
You've got to learn to look at me as the good heavenly provider, that everything you have is from me.
And therefore, it's not just for you.
It is for my kingdom and your neighbor.
Okay.
This is why I'm excited about this series.
Because I struggle with this.
I feel a pull in my heart towards the scarcity mindset.
But I believe that the invitation to Jesus is better.
That if we can embody the abundance mindset, we will live with open hands and generous hearts.
And we will have an abundant life.
I'd love for you to think about, think about the person that you know that is the most generous person that you can think of right now.
Like just take 10 seconds and hopefully, it probably won't take that long to bring to mind.
You probably have their face in your head right now.
Okay, look at their face in your mind.
Are they smiling?
Generous people are happy people.
There's a joy that comes from living generously.
And this is the life Jesus is inviting you to.
And I know what you might be thinking right now because it's what I'm thinking when I'm struggling with the scarcity mindset.
Yeah, but that person that's generous has way more than I have.
Right?
Generosity is not on a scale.
It's not you can be more generous because you have more.
It's all of us.
What can we be generous with what we have?
There are people that have a ton and give a ton.
But the percentage of what they give compared to somebody that has hardly anything and yet continues to give.
And we might look at the person that has more and say, oh, they're really generous.
But they know when they lay their head down in bed at night that they're actually not giving much sacrificially at all.
It's like easy for them to give that much.
Right?
And so we shouldn't be looking at people and rating a scale of how generous they are based on how much they give.
It's about this mindset, scarcity, abundance.
How do we view God and neighbor?
It affects whether we have a good eye or a bad eye.
Does that make sense?
Whew.
That's good because I got lost there for a second.
This leads us to Christ's final teaching for the day that will help us to consider whether we are truly relying on God for our sense of security and happiness or if we have allowed money to take that place in our life.
Kelly, if you want to come up, I'm going to try and wrap up quickly because we are running late.
All right.
Matthew 6, 24.
No one can serve two masters for either he will hate the one and love the other or he will be devoted to the one and despise the other.
You cannot serve God and money.
So Jesus goes on here and he says that even if you like to think your life embodies the abundance mindset, if you're like, yep, I got it.
Everything's from God.
He's the earth, the heavenly provider.
Everything I have comes from him.
I'm good at that.
I got that.
Jesus says, are you believing that in your mind, but then hedging your bets with your stuff?
Even if you think you'd like to think your life reflects the abundance mindset, Jesus says that we often try and have it both ways.
We often try and intellectually and emotionally live under the abundance mindset, but then when budget season comes, when the bonus check hits, when the tax refund hits, it's like, yeah, everything comes from God, but man, this is awesome.
I got more stuff.
Some of your translations here say that you cannot serve God and mammon.
Who has that in their translation?
Anybody?
One?
Yeah.
It's mostly not there anymore.
But the reason that some translations leave it in there is because Jesus often spoke, probably spoke mostly in Aramaic, but the Gospels were written in Greek.
And when Matthew wrote the gospel of Matthew, he wrote all of the words in Greek, except for the word for money he left in Aramaic.
And there's a couple of different theories about why he would have done that, but whatever theory you embrace, as Bible students, we know that Matthew did that on purpose.
So he's trying to draw our attention to something, right?
And so my favorite theory that I think is probably most helpful, and if you're in a small group that listens to the practicing the way message, John Mark uses the other theory, which is fine.
And it all ends up kind of coming out to the same thing.
But most scholars think that the word mammon is actually the noun form of amen.
Amen is trustworthy and true.
So what is a noun of trustworthy and true?
It's the thing you put your trust in.
And so Jesus is saying, you cannot put your trust in God and put your trust in financial stability.
You can't do both.
We think we can, but we can't, because we'll either end up loving the one and hating the other, or loving the one and hating the other.
We can't have it both ways.
We can't hedge our bets with our stuff.
My hunch is that many of us in the room, myself included, would like to think that we serve God as the master of our lives.
But the way that we view and spend our money might reveal that we're trying to serve two masters at the same time.
When we think about our money, does it lead us to feelings of fear or greed?
If so, it's possible that we have an unhealthy relationship with our stuff.
And I'm going to let you all sit with that for a while, because I've been sitting with it for a week and a half.
And I very much so am struggling with this.
It's been very revealing to my heart.
No guilt, no condemnation.
It's Jesus inviting me into a better life.
This is Jesus inviting you into a better life.
A radical, upside-down kingdom that trusts God to provide and leads to peace and generosity.
It doesn't make sense to our earthly eyes, but when we put it in the perspective of eternity, it's the only way to live.
So, covered a lot, big ideas.
And ultimately, these ideas are going to apply to all of us differently.
There are some of you in the room this morning that literally do not have enough money to provide for the absolute basic needs of you and your family.
These principles are going to apply to you differently than they apply to the dinkers with two to six income salaries, right?
It's just the reality.
How these principles apply to our lives are going to apply differently.
And so, I'm not going to try and tell you exactly how you should take these principles and apply them.
For those of you that aren't even being able to pay your bills, the application for you might be to receive generosity from others without feeling shame or guilt.
Knowing that it's God through them that is providing for you.
So, how these principles apply, they apply drastically differently to all of us depending on our situation.
My goal is not to tell you exactly how to apply these principles to your life specifically.
Rather, I would love for you to take this principle to the Holy Spirit in prayer and ask Him what ways He might be inviting you to submit your finances to Him as the Lord and Master of your life.
That being said, this series is called Practicing the Way.
So, it would be foolish of me not to give you something, something that you could do, something that you could practice.
So, here's one practice that I'd love to invite each of you to consider doing this week.
One act of spontaneous generosity outside of your normal routine.
Set aside a specific amount.
It can be a little.
It can be a lot.
If you don't have any margin in your budget at all, maybe you have a possession that is valuable to you that you know would bless somebody else.
Maybe that's how you express to God that you trust Him as the abundant good creator.
I don't know what it looks like for you.
But set aside a specific amount.
Take cash out of an ATM.
Earmark it in your budget.
And take it to God in prayer.
Ask God to give you the opportunity to bless someone.
And then keep your eyes open.
Look around your circles of influence for someone that might be blessed by your act of generosity.
Buy someone behind you in line a coffee.
Anonymously pay for a family's lunch.
Drop off groceries or a gift to someone you know that is in need or has experienced suffering.
Send cash digitally to help a friend with medical bills or an expense that they can't afford to pay.
Buy a gift.
Send it to someone.
Encourage them.
Bless them.
Give a possession away.
Whatever it might be.
Make one act of spontaneous generosity.
And then think about how you felt when you did that act of generosity.
I would love to tell you that the moment you do the act of generosity, you're going to feel a deep sense of joy and happiness.
But I like, I worked on this this week.
And as I was giving the gift, I was like, oh, I kind of would really like to keep this.
Right?
What does that tell me about my heart?
What does that reveal to me about my relationship with God and money?
It's a helpful revelation.
And as I continue this practice week after week, my hope and my prayer is that I continue to come back to the Lord in prayer and say, God, I want to have an abundance mindset, but I often have a scarcity mindset.
So yet again, I am going to give away and see how it makes me feel.
And my hope and my hope and my prayer is that for those of us that are struggling with a scarcity mindset, it's not going to be an immediate.
For some of us, it might be.
You might give the one thing away and you're like, this is the greatest feeling I've ever had in my life.
And for some of you, you might be like me and be like, oh, I kind of liked that thing.
I wanted to keep it, but I'm doing the thing Jesus told me to do.
Yay.
But as we put these things into practice, as we take Jesus at his word, I have followed Jesus long enough to know that doing what he says leads to abundant life.
And that not doing what he says feels good at times, but always falls short of what I wanted to accomplish in my life.
Jesus says, blessed are those who hear what I have to say and do what I have to say.
So I encourage you to pray about how you can put this teaching into action this week.
Consider it how it made you feel.
Get with somebody that loves Jesus that you trust and talk about it.
Talk about how that thing made you feel.
Many of you are going to be in small groups.
You're going to do this together and talk about how did it make you feel?
Why did it make you feel that way?
What might that reveal about your heart?
Sound good?
Let's pray.
Father in heaven, you are so, so good.
You are a loving father who has created out of your generous nature.
You have given us good gifts.
Think about the Garden of Eden.
And throughout the creation account, it says, God gave, God gave, God gave.
And then it says, Adam and Eve took.
We are where we are today as a society because you have freely given and we have taken and run.
God, may we learn as people who profess faith in Jesus to stop taking and to start giving.
For your glory for your glory for our good.
For your glory for our good.
In Jesus' name I pray.
Amen.
Really quick, practical thing that I want to do in light of a message on generosity that was somewhat heavy hitting and hard.
I want to give you thanks for the generosity that you all have expressed.
You probably drove on a new paved and painted parking lot this morning.
Yeah?
Did it feel good on the struts?
I want to do a couple of things.
First, I want to say thank you to all of you that generously, generously gave for us to be able to do that.
Literally in the last five-ish years, for those of you that have been around, even leading back to before the merge,
people have generously been giving, we have replaced our roof, we have replaced our HVAC system, we have replaced our parking lot.
Those are three very big ticket items that will allow us to be here for a long time doing the thing that God is calling us to do in our community.
So thank you all for that very much.
The second thing I want to do, Kevin Sullivan, are you here?
Can you come up here real quick?
Yeah, I knew you were not going to love it.
Kevin Sullivan is our lead trustee.
Many of you maybe have never even seen his face before.
That's because he likes to be behind the scenes, and which is why he's loving this right now.
Yeah.
So Kevin has overseen all of those projects.
Did you do the roof even before I got here?
Did you kind of help?
Oh, no, that's prior to my time.
Okay.
So parking lot, HVAC, on top of many other things that have had to get done.
Kevin has a team of wonderful people.
I don't know everybody that's on your team.
I can think about Rick Sharp, Chris Reinhart, Rodney Gibbons.
A lot of wonderful people come here and spend hours of their time.
And not only them, but their spouses allow them to spend hours of their time fixing our stuff instead of fixing their stuff.
And so I really, I just wanted to take an opportunity to thank you.
I have got you this special Canvas Community Hammer.
I got you a box of hammers to give to all your people that have helped you pull this off.
I was trying to estimate the amount of hours that you have just in the parking lot and your team prepping.
You don't realize that you can't just like rip asphalt up and put it back down.
You have to like do stuff.
Your team has done stuff to make that happen.
And so I want to thank our congregation for the generosity and thank you all for all that you've done.
Super great.
Volunteers are the lifeblood of our ministry.
Trustees are the lifeblood of us being able to do anything in this building without it falling apart.
And so we are so thankful for them.
If you like to fix stuff and you didn't even know that that team existed, find Kevin and he will give you stuff to fix.
That'll be great.
All right, I would love for you to stand and I would love to pray a blessing over you in light of this message on generosity as we exit the building to be the church in our community.
This is from the Scriptures, adapted from the Scriptures.
May God bless you abundantly so that in all things, at all times, you may have all that you need.
May you freely scatter your gifts to the poor.
May God, who supplied seed to the sower and bread for food, also supply and increase your store of seed and enlarge the harvest of your righteousness.
May you be enriched in every way so that you can be generous on every occasion.
And may your generosity result in thanksgiving to God.
Go in peace, church.
Love you.
Thank you.